A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, National Affairs Division, Vice President, Office Files of Mitchell Sviridoff FA577
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, National Affairs Division, Vice President, Office Files of Mitchell Sviridoff
1966-1980
Rockefeller Archive Center
Sviridoff, Mitchell
Ford Foundation
FA577
14.05 Cubic Feet 37 Hollinger document boxes
Mitchell Sviridoff served as Vice President for National Affairs from 1967 to 1980. As Vice President, he supported the establishment of programs intended to address the problems of American cities – including poverty, substandard government services, and racial and economic inequality in the justice system. His tenure spanned an important era of social change in American history that included the Civil Rights Movement, the women's rights movement, and the economic downturn of the 1970s. His files illuminate the Foundation's role in forwarding the social and economic justice goals of these movements as well as its actions and responses to national economic crisis. The Office Files of Mitchell Sviridoff consists of subject files and chronological files. There are subject files for the House Ways and Means Committee and the Tax Reform Act of 1969, the New York City Financial Crisis (1975-1976), the Energy Policy Project (1972-1973), the Welfare Policy Project (1975-1977), the Task Force on Women (1972-1974), the Race and Ethnicity Task Force (1972-1974); Supported Work Programs (1973-1978), and Hispanic Immigration (1979-1980). The chronological files largely pertain to grant activities.
Biographical / Historical
The Foundation's work in urban poverty began with the establishment of the Public Affairs Program in 1952. One of the goals of the new program was to push for greater equality of opportunity for minority groups. In 1965, a National Affairs Division was created to focus on some of the deep-rooted problems facing American society. The program areas under this new National Affairs Division included Social Development, and Urban and Metropolitan Development. The United States and International Affairs Program (USIAP) replaced the National Affairs Division in 1981 after a Foundation-wide reorganization.
Arrangement
The records are arranged into two series.
Collection arrangement is as follows:
Series I. Administrative Subject Files, 1966-1980
Series II. Chronological Correspondence Files, 1975-1978
Scope and Contents
The Office Files of Mitchell Sviridoff document his work as Vice President of the National Affairs Program from 1967 to 1980. His tenure spanned an important era of social change in American history that included the Civil Rights Movement, the women's rights movement, and the economic downturn of the 1970s. Mr. Sviridoff's files reveal the Foundation's role in forwarding the social and economic justice goals of these movements, and its actions and responses to national economic crisis.
The largest group of Mr. Sviridoff's subject files pertains to the House Ways and Means Committee and the Tax Reform Act of 1969. The Tax Reform Act of 1969 sought to curb perceived abuses by wealthy private individuals seeking to shelter their taxable assets by taking advantage of federal tax breaks for charitable institutions. The law impacted the way in which many foundations operated, requiring them to pay out annually in awarded grants a minimum of 5% of their total assets.
Provisions in the law which limited the discretionary autonomy of private foundations in directly awarding grants to individuals and to further political causes were of particular concern to the Ford Foundation. Representatives of the Foundation were called before the House Ways and Means Committee to testify about the proposed reform, which the Foundation opposed because of accusations that it awarded funds for political rather than philanthropic purposes. Perceived to be at stake was the Foundation's work in the Civil Rights Movement and particularly its support for voter registration drives and organizations such as the North Carolina Foundation (1969). The Foundation's awarding of individual study and travel grants to several of Senator Robert F. Kennedy's legislative aides also were questioned.
Documents relating to the Tax Reform Act include correspondence between the Foundation and grantees inquiring whether they had 501(c)(3) status and testimony by Ford President McGeorge Bundy before the House Ways and Means Committee (1969). They also include internal memoranda and reports about the potential impact and possible responses to the Act, statistics from each program listing all grants affected and why, and clippings with references to the Foundation's position and views.
Another set of files details the Foundation's response to the national economic crisis, particularly as it affected New York City from 1975 to 1976. The economic downturn and resulting cuts in municipal funds for social services programs led the Foundation to collaborate with the City and other private foundations to seek ways to help to meet the increased need. The files contain documents and materials from meetings of the multi-foundation Task Force on the New York City Crisis (1976).
Information about the Foundation's response to the energy crisis of the 1970s can also be found in the files. The rise in energy costs precipitated the Foundation's support for the Energy Policy Project (1972-1973), which was funded as a Delegated Authority Project (DAP). Mr. Sviridoff also served as a member of the Nixon Administration's Energy Policy Advisory Committee (1972-1973).
Mr. Sviridoff's subject files also document the Foundation's increasing support for work related to advancing women's rights. Many of these files pertain to the Foundation's Task Force on Women (1972-1974) and the establishment of a women's program in National Affairs. The files contain reports and papers about the changing attitudes toward women and their role in American society and memoranda describe the recruitment of women within the Foundation and among other philanthropic organizations. There are also proposals from organizations requesting seed grants for projects, including Gloria Steinem's Ms. Foundation (1978-1980).
Additional subjects addressed in the files include job creation strategies developed in partnership with the Manpower Demonstration Research Corporation (1974-1980) including programs for "supported work" (1973-1978); Hispanic immigration to the United States (1979-1980); and the establishment of a Police Foundation to encourage alternative and more effective strategies for policing and interacting with communities (1970-1980).
Biographical / Historical
Mitchell Sviridoff was born in New Haven, Connecticut on November 4, 1918. After graduating high school and vocational school, Mr. Sviridoff worked at an aircraft parts assembly plant in Stratford, Connecticut. He held various positions in the labor movement and eventually rose to become President of the Connecticut AFL-CIO. Between 1962 and 1966, he served as Executive Director of Community Progress Inc. (CPI) based in New Haven, Connecticut. CPI, an antipoverty organization founded through a Ford Foundation seed grant, funded grassroots programs in education, employment, housing, youth development, and social services. It quickly became a national model for its human-centered, community-based approach to urban renewal, which focused on providing disadvantaged individuals with the resources, education and employment opportunities they needed for advancement.
In 1966, he became the first Administrator of the New York City Human Resources Administration and was charged with consolidating the City's numerous assistance programs serving low-income communities. During his nine-month tenure, problems developed with staff over intolerable working conditions and he became disenchanted with the agency's unwieldy bureaucratic structure and inertia. He left in 1967 to accept the position of Vice President for National Affairs at the Ford Foundation.
As Vice President for National Affairs, Mr. Sviridoff established a number of programs intended to address the problems of American cities – including poverty, poor quality and delivery of government services, and racial and economic inequality in the justice system. Several of these programs later became separate, free-standing non-profit organizations such as the Vera Institute for Criminal Justice, the Manpower Demonstration Research Corporation, and the Police Foundation.
In addition to his oversight over the Foundation's work with urban renewal, Mr. Sviridoff served as a contact and facilitator between the Foundation and various city, state and the federal governments. These contacts led to his service as a policy advisor to the Nixon Administration on job creation and energy policy during the crises of the 1970s.
In 1980, Mr. Sviridoff left the Ford Foundation to accept a position as the first President of the Local Initiatives Support Corporation, a non-profit organization established by the Foundation to fund grassroots community development efforts. He left Local Initiatives in 1985 to teach at the New School for Social Research. There, he also directed the Kaplan Center for New York City Affairs at the Milano Graduate School, and founded the School's Community Development Research Center. Mr. Sviridoff died on October 21, 2000, at age 81.
Conditions Governing Access
Records more than 10 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
- Administrative Subject Files, 1966-1980; I; 13.67 Cubic Feet 13 letter document boxes
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of subject files. Mr. Sviridoff kept files on grantees and grant projects; the work of his program officers; Ford Foundation policy, program areas and task forces; and external projects, task forces and committees on which he worked. There are also files pertaining to his interests and work and individuals within and without the Foundation with whom he corresponded. Mr. Sviridoff's subject files include the House Ways and Means Committee and the Tax Reform Act of 1969, the New York City Financial Crisis (1975-1976), the Energy Policy Project (1972-1973), the Welfare Policy Project (1975-1977), the Task Force on Women (1972-1974), the Race and Ethnicity Task Force (1972-1974), Supported Work Programs (1973-1978), and Hispanic Immigration (1979-1980).
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - (The) American Assembly -- Correspondence Re: Proposed Forum Topics and Reports, 1973-1980 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - American Bankers Association -- Resource Panel of the Bankers Committee on Urban Affairs -- Correspondence Re: Meetings, Proposal, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - American Ditchley Foundation -- Correspondence Re: Conferences and Meetings, Minutes, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Armsey, James W. -- Memoranda Re: Evaluations of Proposals to Fund Black Colleges, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Atterbury, B. P. -- Memoranda Evaluating and Discerning Ford Foundation Interest in Funding Various Projects, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - B-General -- Brookings Institution, etc., 1975-1980 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Baltimore Trustee Visit, 1978 June 27-28 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Banks and Black Capitalism" (report by David M. Schulte), 1970 September (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bay Area Urban League Address, San Francisco, CA (speech by Mitchell Sviridoff), 1979 April 10 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation -- Memoranda, Statistics, 1971-1980 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Berresford, Susan -- Memoranda, Reports, Background, 1973-1979 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Bohrson, Ralph G. -- Memoranda Re: Leadership Development Program, Report, Proposal, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Boston-Fenway Program, Inc., 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - C-General -- Merrimon Cuninggim, Community News Service, etc. (1 of 2), 1973-1975 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - C-General -- Children's Defense Fund, Congressional Tour, etc. (2 of 2), 1975-1979 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Chafkin, Sol -- Report and Clippings on Nutrition, Background on Community Development Corporations, 1977-1980 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Chalmers, Ellison -- Racial Negotiations Project -- Project Statement, Conference Notes, 1969-1970 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Changing Status of Minorities -- Memoranda and Background on Ford Foundation Project for Reviewing Status of Minorities, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Community Development -- Memoranda, Reports and Background on Ford Foundation's Work in Community Development (1 of 2), 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Community Development -- Memoranda, Reports and Background on Ford Foundation's Work in Community Development (2 of 2), 1972-1978 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Conference on Community Development, Ford Foundation -- Reports, 1971 June 15-16 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - (2nd) Conference on Community Development, Ford Foundation -- Report, 1971 November 3-4 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Conference on National Unity, Sterling Forest Gardens, NY -- Papers, Attendee List (1 of 2), 1969 November 19-20 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Conference on National Unity, Sterling Forest Gardens, NY -- Papers, Attendee List ( 2 of 2), 1969 November 19-20 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Conflict Resolution in Higher Education, Ford Foundation Advisory Committee -- Correspondence, Memoranda, Reports, Background (1 of 2), 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Conflict Resolution in Higher Education, Ford Foundation Advisory Committee -- Correspondence, Memoranda, Reports, Background (2 of 2), 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Congress of Racial Equity (CORE) -- Memoranda Re: Grants, Report on Racial Violence in Cleveland, 1967-1969 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Cooney, Thomas Jr. -- Memoranda and Correspondence Re: Grantees and Ford Foundation Affirmative Action Policy, 1966-1972 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Corrections -- Memoranda, Correspondence and Reports on Correctional Information Service and Criminal Justice Publications (1 of 2), 1971-1976 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Corrections -- Memoranda, Correspondence and Reports on Correctional Information Service and Criminal Justice Publications (2 of 2), 1977-1980 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - D-General -- Education and Urban Programs, etc., 1971-1980 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Day Care -- Memoranda, Reports on Child Care Program Development (1 of 2), 1971-1976 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Day Care -- Memoranda, Reports on Ford Foundation Day Care Policy, Child Care Demonstration Project (2 of 2), 1976-1979 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Dependent Organizations -- Memoranda and Reports on Ford Foundation Division of National Affairs Dependent Organizations, 1972-1975 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - "The Disconnected: Factors Affecting the Participation of Urban Minorities in the Registration and Voting Process" (research paper by Penn Kimball), 1970 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Donahue, Tom -- Memoranda and Reports on Labor Unions in Education, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Dressner, Howard R. -- Memoranda Re: Ford Foundation Policy on Affirmative Action, Lobbying, Foundation Bylaws, etc., 1976-1980 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Drug Abuse Council -- Correspondence, Memoranda, Grant Background (1 of 2), 1970-1973 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Drug Abuse Council -- Correspondence, Memoranda, Grant Background (2 of 2), 1974-1980 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - E-General -- Medgar Evers Fund, etc., 1975-1980 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - East Central Committee for Opportunity (ECCO) -- Correspondence, Memoranda, Background on Grand Jury Investigation, 1974-1977 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - EASYRIDE (Vera Institute) -- Project Background, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Edley, Christopher -- Correspondence and Memoranda Re: Law and Crime, Background, 1968-1972 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Education and Public Policy -- Memoranda Re: Law Center, etc., 1978-1980 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - ELDERWORKS -- Memoranda, Background, 1979 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Ellis, Jim -- Correspondence, Speech for Washington State Convention of Leagues of Women Voters, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Energy Crisis -- Memoranda, Background on Energy Saving, 1979 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Energy Policy Advisory Committee -- Memoranda, Correspondence, Reports, Background (1 of 2), 1972 January-July (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Energy Policy Advisory Committee -- Memoranda, Correspondence, Reports, Background, 1972 August-1973 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Energy Policy Project -- Memoranda, Proposals, Background (1of 2), 1975-1980 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Energy Policy Project -- Reports (2 of 2), 1980 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Environmental Policy -- Memoranda Re: Grants for Environmental Conflict Resolution, Report on Foundation Strategy, 1973-1979 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Esser, George H. -- North Carolina Fund -- Memoranda Re: Evaluations of Projects, Meeting Minutes, Reports of North Carolina Protests and Events (1 of 3), 1968-1969 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Esser, George H. -- North Carolina Fund -- Memoranda Re: Evaluations of Projects, Meeting Minutes, Reports of North Carolina Protests and Events (2 of 3), 1968-1969 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Esser, George H. -- North Carolina Fund -- Memoranda Re: Termination of NCF, Program Objectives, Move to Southern Regional Council (3 of 3), 1970-1974 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Etzioni, Amitai -- Background Re: Leadership, Military Service, 1979-1980 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - F-General -- Trustees' Future Program Planning Project, etc., 1969-1980 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Financial Reviews of Foundation Grantees, 1973-1980 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Ford Foundation Conference on White Workers, 1971 March 8 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Ford Foundation Press Releases, 1973-1980 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Friendly, Fred W. -- Memoranda Re: Public Television Funding, Seminars, Columbia University School of Journalism, etc., 1968-1978 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Fund for the City of New York -- Memoranda, Correspondence, Reports, Proposals, 1968-1979 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - G-General -- Rural Initiative, Black Cooperative Movement and Israel, etc. (1 of 2), 1971-1977 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - G-General -- Papers on American Governance, etc. (2 of 2), 1977-1980 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Ginzberg, Eli -- End of Tour Report on Ford Foundation in India, Correspondence (1 of 2), 1971-1973 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Ginzberg, Eli -- Memoranda Re: Human Resources, Papers on Manpower Policy (2 of 2), 1974-1979 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Gormbley, William -- Memoranda Re: Ford Foundation Pension Plan, 1978-1979 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Greeley, Andrew M. -- Memoranda and Correspondence Re: Controversy over Article on American Values and Ethics, 1974-1978 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Grinker, William -- Memoranda and Background on Electoral Process, 1970-1973 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - H-General -- Health and Human Welfare correspondence and reports, etc. (1 of 2), 1971-1978 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - H-General -- Department of Housing and Urban Development, Teenage Mothers, etc. (2 of 2), 1979 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Haas, Walter A., Jr. -- Correspondence Re: Public Advocates, Inc. and Support for Public Interest Law, 1971 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Hagler, Jon L. -- Ford Foundation Financial Report, Report on International Portfolio Diversification, 1978 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Harrison, Gordon -- Correspondence, Memoranda, Background on Program Advisor, Environmental Policy, etc. (1 of 2), 1969-1971 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Harrison, Gordon -- Correspondence, Memoranda, Background on Program Advisor, Environmental Policy, etc. (2 of 2), 1971-1973 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - House Ways and Means Committee Tax Reform Law of 1969 -- Impact on Ford Foundation Grantmaking (1 of 9) (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - House Ways and Means Committee Tax Reform Law of 1969 -- Impact on Ford Foundation Grantmaking (2 of 9) (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - House Ways and Means Committee Tax Reform Law of 1969 -- Impact on Ford Foundation Grantmaking (3 of 9) (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - House Ways and Means Committee Tax Reform Law of 1969 -- Impact on Ford Foundation Grantmaking (4 of 9) (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - House Ways and Means Committee Tax Reform Law of 1969 -- Impact on Ford Foundation Grantmaking (5 of 9) (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - House Ways and Means Committee Tax Reform Law of 1969 -- Impact on Ford Foundation Grantmaking (6 of 9) (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - House Ways and Means Committee Tax Reform Law of 1969 -- Impact on Ford Foundation Grantmaking (7 of 9) (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - House Ways and Means Committee Tax Reform Law of 1969 -- Impact on Ford Foundation Grantmaking (8 of 9) (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - House Ways and Means Committee Tax Reform Law of 1969 -- Impact on Ford Foundation Grantmaking (9 of 9) (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Housing -- Grant Information on National Project on Housing and Urban Law (1 of 2), 1967-1968 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Housing -- Reports and Publications on Ford Foundation Housing Programs (2 of 2), 1972-1979 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Howe, Harold II -- Writings on Economics of Helping the Poor, Higher Education and Minorities, etc., 1975-1979 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Human Resources Administration -- Proposal for Career Development Program, Memoranda, 1967-1968 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Human Resources Administration, Community Development Agency -- Correspondence, Proposals (1of 2), 1967 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Human Resources Administration, Community Development Agency -- Correspondence, Proposals (2 of 2), 1968 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - I-General -- Institute for Civil Justice, Israel, etc., 1968-1979 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Immigration -- Memoranda, Correspondence, Reports on International Migration and Refugees (1 of 4), 1979-1980 March (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Immigration -- Memoranda and Paper on Hispanic Americans (2 of 4), 1980 May-December (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Immigration -- "Mexican and Caribbean Migration to the United States" (report by Wayne A. Cornelius) (3 of 4), 1979 April (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Immigration -- "Mexican and Caribbean Migration to the United States" (report by Wayne A. Cornelius) (4 of 4), 1979 April (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Indians [American, Northeast] -- Gay Head, MA Lawsuit, 1976-1977 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Institute for Community Studies, Queens College -- Correspondence, Proposal, Papers, 1968-1970 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Institute for Congress -- Correspondence Re: Grant Support, 1973-1976 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Institute for Law and Social Research (INSLAW) -- Memoranda and Correspondence Re: Grant, 1976-1978 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Institute for Mediation and Conflict Resolution -- Correspondence Re: Grant Support, 1975-1977 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Intermediate School 201 (I.S. 201) Demonstration Project -- Correspondence, Proposals, Clippings, 1967-1969 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - International Division, Ford Foundation -- Memoranda Re: Budget, 1979-1980 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Internship Program at Ford Foundation Division of National Affairs, 1977-1980 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - J-General -- Jobs, etc., 1970-1980 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Jaffe, Sanford -- Memoranda Re: Cable Television and Other Grant Proposals, 1968-1979 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - James Weldon Johnson Community Center -- Correspondence, Papers, 1967-1969 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Job Creation Strategy -- Correspondence and Reports on Ford Foundation and Government Strategies (1 of 2), 1975-1976 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Job Creation Strategy -- Correspondence, Memoranda, Reports, Background (2 of 2), 1976-1977 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Job Satisfaction -- Correspondence, Memoranda, Reports on Ford Foundation Studies (1 of 3), 1972 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Job Satisfaction -- Sviridoff/Ford Foundation Interest in Work Studies (2 of 3), 1973 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Job Satisfaction -- Worker Alienation (3 of 3), 1973-1974 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Joint Center for Political Studies -- Correspondence Re: Carl Stokes, 1977-1979 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Juvenile and Children's Programs -- Correspondence and Reports on Child Advocacy, Nutrition, etc. (1 of 4), 1974-1975 (Box 14, Folder 6)